Moving on to meningitis, this is inflammation of the leptomeninges.
In order to understand this, let's go back and remind ourselves that here is the skull,
and then tightly attached to the skull is a layer of the meninges called the dura,
and then here is the brain, and then tightly attached to the brain is a layer of the meninges called the pia.
And then in between, you've got these web-like spaces, which then result in a layer called the arachnoid.
And so these are the three layers of the meninges, the pia, the arachnoid, and the dura.
And some people like to say that there is a pad in between the brain and the skull.
Now, the dura is called the dura because it's thick and durable.
And the arachnoid and the pia tend to be very light and thin,
and so they're called the leptomeninges or the light meninges.
And with that in mind, then you can understand that meningitis is inflammation of the leptomeninges,
i.e. the pia and the arachnoid.
Here's a picture of meningitis, and you can clearly see the brain.
And so when you see the brain, you're looking at the pia.
The dura would be durable and thick, and you would have difficulty seeing the surface of the brain clearly.
And so, again, within the pia, you can see here that you've got all this inflammation and exudate and pus,
and so this represents actually a bacterial meningitis.
Meningitis is most commonly due to an infectious agent.
It's very high yield to know the agents and the age groups in which they occur.
So, for example, in a neonate, the three most common causes are group B strep, E. coli, and listeria.
A group B strep and E. coli can arise from the vaginal canal during the birthing process.
In fact, in the case of group B strep, we'll test women in the third trimester to see whether they're colonized with group B strep,
and if they are, we actually treat them with antibiotics to decrease the risk of exposure of the baby during the birthing process.
Neisseria meningitis is the most common cause in children and teenagers.
Board examiners like you to know that this enters through the nasopharynx and then goes to the blood,
and from the blood, it gets to the meninges.
Strep pneumo is the most common cause in adults and the elderly.
H flu would be a common cause in non-vaccinated infants.
Board examiners like to go after that, especially with all the controversy over immunizations.
Coxsackievirus is the most common viral cause of meningitis.
It has a fecal-oral transmission, and then fungi can cause meningitis in immunocompromised individuals.
Patients with meningitis present with a classic triad of headache, neck stiffness, and fever.
The headache and neck stiffness are due to the fact that the meninges are inflamed,
and of course, the meninges wrap around the brain, giving headache and neck stiffness
because when you bend the neck, you're going to feel the pain of the meninges being inflamed.
Fever, of course, because the patient has an infection.
In addition, you might see photophobia, especially with virus.
It's much more common to see photophobia.
Vomiting can be present, and altered mental status can also be seen.
When you suspect meningitis, you'll do a lumbar puncture.
The goal is to sample the fluid in the subarachnoid space and then to analyze it.
Board examiners like you to know that you should normally stick the needle between L4 to L5,
the level of the iliac crest.
The reason being, which is particularly high yield, is that the spinal cord ends at L2,
but the subarachnoid space and the cauda equina, they continue to S2.
And so, again, if you stick a needle at L4 to L5, you'll be able to get the subarachnoid space without hitting the cord.
Board examiners also like you to know that when you do an LP, you're actually going to go through a few layers.
You go through the skin, and then you cross the ligaments.
Then you'll enter the epidural space.
You'll cross the dura, and then you'll cross the arachnoid, but you will not pierce the pia,
and that's particularly high yield.
Again, you will not pierce the pia.
Once you obtain your fluid, you can then analyze the fluid to determine the cause.
So, for example, neutrophils with low glucose would be seen with bacteria.
Now, neutrophils, of course, because that's the cell that fights bacterial infection,
and then in addition, the glucose would be low because the bacteria, they consume glucose.
Now, recall that the normal glucose in the CSF is about two-thirds of that what is present in the serum.
So, for example, if the serum glucose is normally 100, then the normal CSF glucose would be about 66.
And so, bacteria, they'll consume glucose, giving you a low glucose, so neutrophils plus low glucose.
In addition, you'll often see a positive gram stain and culture.
In the case of viral meningitis, you'll see lymphocytes, and that's because lymphocytes fight virus.
And then you'll see a normal CSF glucose, and that's because virus does not consume glucose.
I mean, if you want to talk about virus, the discussion is are they living or are they dead,
so forget about the question about eating glucose.
They do not consume glucose, and so the glucose will be normal.
And finally, in the case of fungal meningitis, you'll also see lymphocytes.
However, because fungi consume glucose, there'll be a low CSF glucose as opposed to the viral meningitis.
One last high yield point, and that is that the complications of meningitis are classically seen with bacterial meningitis.
Again, the idea here is that there really is no space in the head except for the brain.
It's a very tight space.
And if you get bacterial meningitis, you get a ton of pus and inflammation and inflammatory exudate,
and that then creates pressure on the brain, which can then cause the brain to herniate.
And when you get a herniation, that's what then results in death.
And of course, this would only be seen with bacteria because it's with bacteria that you get the massive amounts of exudate and pus, etc.
Now, another series of complications with bacterial meningitis are all based on the healing process.
After you get bacterial meningitis, you're going to have massive tissue damage, which will then result in extensive healing and fibrosis.
And that fibrosis can knock out the normal pathways of the CSF, giving you hydrocephalus.
It can damage the nerves as they exit the brain, so for example, giving you hearing loss.
And it can scar the surface of the brain, increasing the risk for seizures.
But the take-home point here is that all of this would be primarily seen with bacterial meningitis.
And that concludes our section on meningitis.